Finding aid to the Helen Rachel Williams papers CA.MS.00349
Smith College Archives
Helen Rachel Williams papers
1888-1910
Smith College Archives
Williams, Helen Rachel, 1871-1957
CA.MS.00349
0.625 linear feet (2 containers)
Smith College Class of 1892. Contains correspondence and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials in the Helen Rachel Williams Papers were donated to the College Archives by Pat Jennings. They were donated in the name of Nicole Jennings, Class of 2004. The Jennings family is not related to Helen Rachel Williams. Pat Jennings purchased this collection of letters from a dealer and subsequently donated them to the Smith College Archives.
Biographical / Historical
Helen Rachel Williams was born in Canton, Massachusetts on August 6, 1871. She was the daughter of W.J. Williams and Mira G. Draper Williams. Her father was a manufacturer. Helen was educated at the Berkeley School and was a self-professed Unitarian. She entered Smith College in 1888, and received her B.A. degree in 1892. During college, she lived at Washburn House and, not surprisingly, most of her friends and correspondents lived in that house during college as well. After graduation, Williams moved back to Canton, Massachusetts and became a teacher in the Canton school system, teaching from 1895-1912. She never married and died January 24, 1957.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains primarily letters written to Helen Williams from her Smith College friends. Her and her friends write during college and afterward, telling each other of their lives and activities. Other correspondents include several male friends and colleagues, as well as her siblings. The collection also contains two photographs of the room Helen occupied in Washburn House, probably during the 1891-1892 academic year. An index of letters is avaliable.
Williams, Helen Rachel, 1871-1957
- Correspondence: American Society for Psychical Research, 1907 (Box 1471.1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence: Association of Collegiate Alumnae Boston Branch, 1892-1894 (Box 1471.1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence: Barry, Florence (1893), 1891-1894 (Box 1471.1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence: Barton, Blake, undated (Box 1471.1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence: Bourland, Caroline "Carrie" "Psyche" (1893) (Box 1471.1, Folder 5)
  General
  See also: 42. Bourland, Caroline 1891-1904
- Correspondence: Burnham, Gertrude, 1895-1898 (Box 1471.1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence: Darling, Frances (1893), 1892-1898 (Box 1471.1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence: DeMerritte, Edwin-of the Berkeley School, Boston, MA, 1888-1889 (Box 1471.1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence: Dickerson, May Florence, 1892-1895 (Box 1471.1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence: Dole, Mary "Mollie" Mitchell (ex-1893), 1892-1904 (Box 1471.1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence: Dunbar, Olivia Howard (1894), 1892-1903; undated (Box 1471.1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence: Easton, Marie Louise, 1899; 1901 (Box 1471.1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence: Granger, Edith (1891), 1890 (Box 1471.1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence: Haven, Katherine (1892), 1894-1907 (Box 1471.1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence: Hendrie, Jennie Frances (ex-1892), 1890-1892 (Box 1471.1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence: Howard, Susan A., undated (Box 1471.1, Folder 16)
- Correspondence: Jepson, Harry S., 1894 (Box 1471.1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence: Landon, Grace (1893), 1889 (Box 1471.1, Folder 18)
- Correspondence: Landon, Mary (1893), 1889-1890 (Box 1471.1, Folder 19)
- Correspondence: Lane, Grace (1893), 1892-1894 (Box 1471.1, Folder 20)
- Correspondence: Lathrop, Clara S., 1891 (Box 1471.1, Folder 21)
- Correspondence: Love, Grace (1893), 1892 (Box 1471.1, Folder 22)
- Correspondence: Lowry, Ethel C., 1896 (Box 1471.1, Folder 23)
- Correspondence: Mansfield, Christine (1892), 1892-1893 (Box 1471.1, Folder 24)
- Correspondence: Mills, Harriet C. (1893), 1892 (Box 1471.1, Folder 25)
- Correspondence: Morse, Herbert A., 1893 (Box 1471.1, Folder 26)
- Correspondence: Murkland, Charlotte "Lottie" (1893), 1891-1898 (Box 1471.1, Folder 27)
- Correspondence: Noyes, Bertha L. (1894), 1893 (Box 1471.1, Folder 28)
- Correspondence: Paul, Florence Helen (1891), 1898; 1901 (Box 1471.1, Folder 29)
- Correspondence: Peterson, Helen (ex. 1893) (Box 1471.1, Folder 30)
- Correspondence: Procter, Adeline W. (1893), 1892-1896 (Box 1471.1, Folder 31)
- Correspondence: Reed, Frank H., 1906-1907 (Box 1471.1, Folder 32)
- Correspondence: Scovill, Florence May (1893) (Box 1471.1, Folder 33)
  See also: Dole, Mary Mitchell 1894-1904, n.d.
- Correspondence: Scovill, William L., 1903-1904 (Box 1471.1, Folder 34)
- Correspondence: Smith, Amy Gertrude, 1897-1898 (Box 1471.1, Folder 35)
- Correspondence: Timmerman, Charlotte (ex-1893), 1890 (Box 1471.1, Folder 36)
- Correspondence: Waldo, Grace (ex-1892) (Box 1471.1, Folder 37)
  See also: Wyman, Evelyn 1892-1902
- Correspondence: Watt, Edith, 1890 (Box 1471.1, Folder 38)
- Correspondence: White, Marion Ballantyne (ex-1892), 1889-1904 (Box 1471.2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence: Williams, Anne (sister), 1889 (Box 1471.2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence: Williams, Roger (brother), 1899 (Box 1471.2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence: Wyatt, Mabel Preston (1893), 1891-1893 (Box 1471.2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence: Wyatt, Mabel Preston (1893), 1894-1903; undated (Box 1471.2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence: Wyman, Evelyn (ex-1894), 1891-1893 (Box 1471.2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence: Unidentified individuals, 1891-1910 (Box 1471.2, Folder 7)
- Invitations, 1895-1905; undated (Box 1471.2, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous, 1888; undated (Box 1471.2, Folder 9)
- Photographs, 1892 (Box 1471.2, Folder 10)